Professor Dave again, let’s talk about midsegments.
We just looked at all kinds of bisectors and
other lines that pertain to triangles, so
let’s learn just one more type.
A midsegment of a triangle is a line segment
that joins the midpoints of two sides of the
triangle.
Every triangle will therefore have precisely
three midsegments, and these three line segments
form another triangle, the midsegment triangle.
Since the vertices of the midsegment triangle
are the midpoints of these sides, we can know
that the segments on either side of a midpoint
are equal to one another.
This is signified by these tick marks, one
line here and one line here means these are
the same.
Two lines here and two lines here means these
are the same as each other, but not necessarily
the same as the segments with one tick mark.
Three tick marks, same idea.
Furthermore, the triangle midsegment theorem
states that any midsegment of a triangle is
parallel to one of the sides of the triangle
and is also precisely half the length of that
side.
So here we can see one midsegment and the
side of the triangle that it is parallel to.
The midsegment is half the length of the side,
and since the side is split up into two equal
sections, the midsegment is equal to both
of these two sections.
We can say the same thing for the other two
midsegments and their corresponding parallel
sides.
This allows us to draw all kinds of figures
like this one, where some lengths are given
and others can be determined.
If we know the length of this midsegment,
we know this side length.
If we know this other side length, then we
know the length of this other midsegment.
There’s plenty of algebra we can do with
this theorem, so let’s check comprehension.